<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Remy Chaput</title><link>/author/remy-chaput/</link><atom:link href="/author/remy-chaput/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Remy Chaput</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 22:06:02 +0200</lastBuildDate><image><url>/images/icon_hu62f16b166d299cea1530d18dc13c60c6_452_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>Remy Chaput</title><link>/author/remy-chaput/</link></image><item><title>Py3status Random Wallpaper</title><link>/project/py3status-wallpaper/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 22:06:02 +0200</pubDate><guid>/project/py3status-wallpaper/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/rchaput/py3status-random-wallpaper/" title="Pystatus-Random-Wallpaper" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Py3status Random Wallpaper&lt;/a> is a module for
&lt;a href="https://github.com/ultrabug/py3status/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Py3status&lt;/a> (which is itself a replacement for the defaul i3status in i3bar) that allows you to
change your wallpaper. Each time the module is loaded (for example, when the i3bar is started), it will
pick a random wallpaper amongst your library. You can also directly click on the module to change the wallpaper.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This module was made with high configurability in mind, and you can tweak several parameters, such as:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>the folders which will be scanned for wallpapers&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the buttons used to trigger a new change&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the command used to set the wallpaper (by default, uses
&lt;a href="https://feh.finalrewind.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">feh&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>an optional list of ignored files&lt;/li>
&lt;li>and others&amp;hellip;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>XDG-Prefs</title><link>/project/xdgprefs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 21:36:46 +0200</pubDate><guid>/project/xdgprefs/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/rchaput/xdg-prefs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">XDG-Prefs&lt;/a> is an Open-Source tool to manage your default applications on GNU/Linux, with a simple but efficient GUI.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On GNU/Linux systems, each file has a type, named the
&lt;a href="https://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Specifications/shared-mime-info-spec/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MIME Type&lt;/a> (or Media Type), based on the
&lt;a href="https://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Specifications/mime-apps-spec/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">XDG Specifications&lt;/a> by
&lt;a href="https://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Freedesktop&lt;/a>. Your system maintains a database that specifies the
default application you want to use for each MIME Type ; this database is available through the official
&lt;code>xdg-mime&lt;/code> tool, but the command-line interface is not suited for easy management (you must remember the
exact name of the MIME Type for example).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/rchaput/xdg-prefs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">XDG-Prefs&lt;/a> offers a simple GUI that allows you to view and modify this database easily ; it
is built upon the same standard specifications, meaning that your preferences will be recognized by
all other applications (typically, when you double-click on a file in your File Explorer).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Such a tool is commonly found in Desktop Environments, such as &lt;em>Gnome&lt;/em> or &lt;em>KDE&lt;/em>, but not in Window Managers,
such as &lt;em>i3wm&lt;/em>.
&lt;a href="https://github.com/rchaput/xdg-prefs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">XDG-Prefs&lt;/a> is desktop-agnostic, meaning that you can use it on Gnome, KDE, or even i3.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>